A Finding Aid to the Sheldon Ross Gallery Records, 1970-2007, bulk 1976-1995, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Sheldon Ross Gallery records
circa 1970-2007
bulk 1976-1995
Archives of American Art
Sheldon Ross Gallery
AAA.shelrosg
Archival Resource Key
2.2 Linear feet
The records of the Sheldon Ross Gallery, Birmingham, Michigan, measure 2.2 linear feet and are dated 1970-2007, with the bulk of materials dating from 1976-1995. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files. About half of the materials relate to Romare Bearden's work and his relationship with Sheldon Ross, the gallery owner. Also included are artists' files regarding George Grosz and Michigan artists. The contents of artists' files vary but generally include biographical information, printed materials and photographic images. The collection also contains correspondence, exhibition files, and photographs documenting the gallery's activities.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2010 and 2022 by Phyllis Ross, widow of Sheldon Ross.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
The Sheldon Ross Gallery (1975-1993), Birmingham, Michigan, and later Sheldon Ross Fine Arts and Sheldon Ross Fine Arts LLC (1993-2000) were operated by Sheldon Ross until his death in 2000. The Sheldon Ross Gallery was the only gallery in the Detroit area to consistently show German Expressionist art, emphasizing graphics. However, the gallery and Ross are best known for their early and continued support of Romare Bearden's work. The exhibition history shows a balance between an interest in local artists and an effort to offer diverse artwork from broad based sources.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Sheldon Ross Gallery, Birmingham, Michigan, measure 2.2 linear feet and are dated 1970-2007, with the bulk of materials dating from 1976-1995. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files. About half of the materials relate to Romare Bearden's work and his relationship with Sheldon Ross, the gallery owner. Also included are artists' files regarding George Grosz and Michigan artists. The contents of artists' files vary but generally include biographical information, printed materials and photographic images. The collection also contains correspondence, exhibition files, and photographs documenting the gallery's activities.
The gallery records document its exhibition history, exhibition reviews, sales of artwork, and Ross' significant projects. Also included are photographs and slides documenting much of the artwork exhibited. Materials relating to Romare Bearden include exhibition files, writings by and about Bearden and his artwork, and correspondence between Bearden and Ross during the years 1976-1989. There are many catalogs of Bearden's solo exhibitions at galleries, museums, and institutions, as well as exhibition reviews from newspapers and magazines, and images of Bearden's works.
The gallery exhibited other well-known artists including 20th century American artists and German Expressionists, notably George Grosz, who instructed Bearden at the Art Students League in New York. Found in the records are exhibition catalogues, price lists, inventory cards and artists' background materials. Also found is correspondence with museums, artists and clients, and slides and other photographic material of artwork offered by the gallery. Of note is correspondence between Sheldon Ross and the FBI concerning Ross' participation as an expert witness in a prosecution of individuals who were involved in Romare Bearden forgeries.
There are drawings of Sheldon Ross and The Sheldon Ross Galley by his son, Robert Ross. Photographs are of Sheldon Ross and Romare Bearden, Sheldon Ross with family and friends, and the predecessor gallery, Middle Earth Gallery.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 7 Series. Materials are generally arranged by record type and chronologically thereafter.
Missing Title
Series 1: Gallery History, 1976-2000 (Box 1, OV 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1982-1999 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1976-1988 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 4: Artists' Files, 1968-2007 (Boxes 1-2, 6; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1976-2000 (Box 2; 2 folders; OV 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Drawings by Robert Ross, after 1975, (OV 5; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographic Materials, circa 1970-2000 (Boxes 2-3, OV 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Drawings; Expressionism (Art); Arts -- Forgeries; Art galleries, Commercial -- Michigan; Art Students League (New York, N.Y.) -- Faculty; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988; Grosz, George, 1893-1959; Middle Earth Gallery; Ross, Sheldon, 1925-2000
- Gallery History, 1976-2000; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, OV 4
  Scope and Contents note
  Material concerning the Sheldon Ross Gallery history consists of newspaper clippings, press releases and mailings to clients. There also is a 1996 videotaped panel discussion at the Snug Harbor Cultural Center in Staten Island, New York in which Sheldon Ross discusses his role as an art dealer and collector. The Middle Earth Gallery folder consists of press releases and photographs of Sheldon Ross in the Gallery with local artists.
  - Sheldon Ross Gallery, 1976-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Middle Earth Gallery, (Predecessor of Sheldon Ross Gallery), 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Middle Earth Gallery, Photograph, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
    From Box 1, folder 2
- Correspondence, 1982-1999; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Sheldon Ross Gallery correspondence includes letters between Sheldon Ross and the Whitney Museum concerning Ross' loan to the Museum of a work by Milton Avery and correspondence with galleries and collectors concerning sales of artwork. Special Agent Catherine Begley of the FBI corresponded with Ross regarding his participation as an expert witness in a prosecution for alleged forgery of Bearden's work. Also found are cards from friends and associates sent on the occasion of Sheldon Ross' 60th birthday.
  - Sheldon Ross Gallery Correspondence, 1982-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sheldon Ross 60th Birthday Cards, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Exhibition Files, 1976-1988; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  This series includes various exhibition lists with prices and write-ups concerning artists such as Kaethe Kollwitz, Max Beckmann, Karl Staber, John Sloan and Oscar Bluemner.
  The "Die Shaffenden" exhibition, held at the University of Manitoba, in Winnipeg, Canada, is documented by inventory cards and price lists, loan correspondence, and an exhibition announcement.
  - Exhibition Lists, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Die Shaffenden Exhibition"(1976), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Artists' Files, 1967-2007; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 6
  The artists' files comprise about half of the Sheldon Ross Gallery records and most of these materials concern Romare Bearden. Also featured are records relating to George Grosz and Michigan artists Sue Lindburg [Browse], Susan Hauptman, Ron Morosan, Leo Mardirosian, Caroline Court, Israel Kaplanski, Gordon Orears and Allie McGhee. The types and quantities of materials vary from one artist to another.
  The Romare Bearden materials include correspondence between Romare Bearden and Sheldon Ross spanning almost twenty years as well as correspondence with publishing houses, other galleries, and museums. Biographical material includes a recording of a 1988 National Public Radio program entitled "Collage: From the Life and Art of Romare Bearden," a list of solo exhibitions from 1940-1980, and a selected bibliography concerning the artist and his work. Exhibition files include price lists, drafts of writings, correspondence, and some printed material. There also is a writing by Bearden, "Rectangular Structures in My Montage Paintings" as well as copies of essays about Bearden and his work.
  Materials concerning George Grosz include newspaper clippings, price lists and exhibition catalogs in addition to many photographs of works. The Michigan artists file contains some biographical material, newspaper clippings, photographs of artworks, and sketches of "art awards" by an unidentified person.
  Additional material concerning Michigan artists is found in a folder titled "Exhibition Lists" folder in Series 3, Exhibition Files.
  - Romare Bearden, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Biographical Material, 1980-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters to Sheldon Ross, 1974-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters from Sheldon Ross, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Harry N. Abrams Inc., 1976-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, June Kelly and Jerald Melberg Gallery Inc., 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence, 1971-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Dealers and Customers, 1982-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Estate Papers, 1980-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Writings by and about Romare Bearden, 1969-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Exhibitions Held at Sheldon Ross Gallery, 1971-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - The Mint Museum, 1970-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Exhibition, Romare Bearden, 1970-1980 (1980-1981), Mint Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Exhibition, The Art of Romare Bearden (1984), Grand Rapids Art Museum, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Exhibition, The Portrayal of the Black Musician in American Art (1986-1987), California Afro-American Museum, Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - The Studio Museum in Harlem, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Exhibition, Memory and Metaphor: The Art of Romare Bearden, 1940-1987 (1991), The Studio Museum in Harlem, Museum of Contemporary Art Chicago, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Exhibitions at Sheldon Ross Gallery, 1971-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Group Exhibitions, circa 1970-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Solo Exhibitions, New York, 1968-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Solo Exhibitions, Other, 1986-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Exhibitions Held Elsewhere, 1992, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Folder, "The Painted Sounds of Romare Bearden", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Invoices, The J. L. Hudson Gallery, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1971-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Clippings, 1971-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Clippings, 1971-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Photographs, Artwork "Sold" and "Unsold,", after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Transparencies, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Reproductions, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Reproductions of Bearden's Work, 1991-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
  - George Grosz, 1979-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - George Grosz Photographic Material, 1976-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Michigan Artists, 1978-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Printed Material, 1976-2000; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.2
  Found are gallery exhibition reviews which appeared mostly in Detroit area newspapers. The exhibition announcements are both postcards and more elaborate materials, including some posters.
  - Clippings, 1976-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Announcements, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Announcements, 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
    From Box 2, folder 5
- Drawings by Robert Ross, after 1975; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet OV 5
  This file contains two drawings by Sheldon Ross' son, Robert Ross; one is of the gallery and the other of Sheldon Ross in his gallery.
  - Oversized Drawings by Robert Ross, after 1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1970-2000; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, OV 5
  The core photographic material includes a collection of 35-mm color slides of artwork by Romare Bearden and George Grosz. There also are photographs of artwork, Sheldon Ross, and others involved in the galllery.
  - Photographs of Sheldon Ross, Friends and Family, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 5
  - Artwork, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transparencies and Negatives of Artwork, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Slides of Artwork, 1975-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    3 slide boxes
  - Photographs, after 1970; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
    From Box 2, folder 6